United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, Local 210 Records 1984.0016
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, Local 210 Records
undated, 1901-1986
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1984.0016
4 Linear Feet
The United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners was founded on 8 August 1881. In 1892, sixty-eight carpenters in the Stamford area, dissatisfied with low wages and long workweeks, agreed to join the union. With the assistance of Frank Duffy, president of the New York UBCJ Council, UBCJ Local 210 of Stamford was organized. The charter was granted on 14 October 1897.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
The records of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners, Local 210 were deposited at Connecticut Labor Archives, University of Connecticut on 9 May 1984.
Arrangement
Series I: Administrative Files (undated, 1908-1986) is comprised of eight subseries. The first subseries, Lists and Directories (1929-1986), contains various guides and directories to UBCJ and Connecticut labor organizations. They are arranged alphabetically, by the name of the organization. The second subseries, Constitutions (1916-1955), contains the constitutions of the UBCJ and UBCJ- affiliated locals. Also included is a 1916 Connecticut Federation of Labor constitution. Constitutions is arranged in chronological order. The third subseries, By-laws (undated, 1915-1971), contains the by-laws and constitutions of various UBCJ locals that later merged with Stamford Local 210. By-laws is arranged numerically by local number. The fourth subseries, Agreements (undated, 1908-1981), consists of agreements between UBCJ locals and city residential and commercial contractors. Included in this subseries is a 1935 Journeyman Barber's International Union of America manual of Common Procedure. Agreements is arranged in chronological order. The fifth subseries, Anniversaries and Celebrations (1969-1977), contains labor award ceremonies and bound volumes commemorating local and national UBCJ anniversaries. Anniversaries and Celebrations is arranged in chronological order. The sixth subseries, Finance (1922-1976), contains miscellaneous fiscal records and financial reports that belonged to Local 210. They are arranged in chronological order. The seventh subseries, Publications (undated) contains various UBCJ newsclippings, primarily from the Stamford area. Also included is a folder containing several building and trade brochures and advertisements. The eighth subseries, Photographs (undated, 1950-1970), contains various UBCJ photographs and postcards, as well as the plans for the UBCJ Executive Headquarters in Stamford, Connecticut.
Series II: Minute books (undated, 1901-1977) is comprised of meeting minutebooks belonging to individual UBCJ locals that later merged with Local 210 in Stamford. Within each local, the Minute books are arranged in chronological order.
History
The Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners was founded on 8 August 1881. Carpenters unions and trade organizations throughout the United States met in Chicago and elected Peter McGuire—a young carpenter who had successfully organized carpenters in the St. Louis area—secretary, and Gabriel Edmondsen of Washington, D.C. president of the newly formed union. Under McGuire's dynamic leadership, the UBCJ was the largest trade union in America by 1890. During the 1890s the Carpenters played a major role in Labor's struggle for an eight-hour workday and were instrumental in the establishment of Labor Day as a national holiday. In 1894, Peter McGuire and the Carpenters joined Samuel Gompers to form the American Federation of Labor.
Local 1713 of South Norfolk was the first to receive a charter in the area by Local 746 of Norfolk in 1891. Other early UBCJ in western Connecticut Local 100J of New Milford (1902), Local 119 of Ridgefield (1906), Local 409 of New Canaan (1910), and Local 1200 of Wilton (1912). The first contract negotiated by Local 713 called for an hourly wage of 22.5 cents and a sixty-hour workweek.
In 1892, sixty-eight carpenters in the Stamford area, dissatisfied with low wages and long work weeks, agreed to form a union. With the assistance of Frank Duffy, president of the New York UBCJ Council, UBCJ Local 210 of Stamford was organized. The charter was granted on 14 October 1897. John T. Flynn was elected financial secretary and served Local 210 in various capacities until his death in 1940. Prior to Local 210's existence, carpenters in the Stamford area worked 10 - 12 hours a day, six days a week at a rate of $1.50 to $2.00 per day. Local 210's first negotiated contract established a nine-hour day at a rate of 30 cents an hour. Local 210 continued to grow steadily through the mid-1920s. In 1924 membership stood at six hundred and eighty carpenters; wages had increased to $1.12 per hour and the workweek was further reduced to 45 hours. That same year, Carpenters Hall was built in Stamford area. It was torn down in 1971.
Local 210's growth was severely curtailed by the economic depression, beginning in 1929. By the mid-1930s membership dropped below fifty and wages fell below a dollar an hour—from pre-Depression high of $1.25. Recovery did not begin until 1941 and the United States' entry into the Second World War. At the fiftieth anniversary of Local 210's founding in 1942, there were 360 members and the wage rate was $1.87 per hour.
During the post-war period, Local 210 membership continued to grow. Unlike many smaller locals, which were unable to compete effectively for large jobs, Local 210 was able to take advantage of urban expansion and negotiate large increases for its members. By the late 1960s total UBCJ membership reached 10,000 members. Economic recession, combined with an expansion of the non-union sector of the construction industry in the early 1920s, cut UBCJ membership in half. Unlike many other locals, however, Local 210 has been able to maintain a steady rate of growth, numbering approximately 3000 dues-paying members in 1986. Contributing to 210's success has been a series of timely mergers with older UBCJ locals. In November 1968, the 72 members of Stamford Local 1700 voted to merge with Local 210. The 99 members of New Canaan Local 409 followed them in 1969. In 1977, 260 members of Norfolk Local 246 voted to merge with Local 210. This placed the towns of Ridgefield, Norfolk, Darien, New Canaan, and Stamford under the jurisdiction of a single local. More recently, as a consequence of the merger with Local 1717 in 1979, Local 210's jurisdiction was expanded to the entire state of Connecticut for shops and mills under industrial charter.
Scope and Content
The collection contains administrative files, publications, legal and financial records, newspaper clippings, photographs, brochures and advertisements, and minute books documenting the activities of the union and its members.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Carpenter, 1906-1938 Dodd Periodicals
Carpenter's news, 1970-1984 Dodd Periodicals
Constitutions; Periodicals; Carpenters; Woodworkers; Ridgefield (inhabited place); Anniversaries; Stamford (inhabited place); Wilton (inhabited place); Joiners; Connecticut (state); Norfolk (inhabited place); Labor unions; New Canaan (inhabited place); Danbury (inhabited place); Darien (inhabited place); Festivals; Greenwich (inhabited place); Hartford (inhabited place); Middletown (inhabited place); Photographs; Correspondence; Publications (documents); Photocopies; Contracts; Administrative records; Carpentry; Financial Records; Collective labor agreements; Newsletters; bylaws (administrative records); Blueprints (reprographic copies).
- Series I: Administrative Files, undated, 1908-1986
  - Subseries A: Lists and Directories, 1920-1986
    - Connecticut State Council, officers, 1964-1965 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - Connecticut Bureau of Labor Statistics, Directory of Labor Organizations in Connecticut, 1906 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - List of UBCJ union label shops and firms, 1930, 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - Town of Stamford, list of taxable real estate, 1929 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Subseries B: Constitutions, 1916-1971
    - Connecticut Federation of Labor, 1916 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
    - Stamford Central Labor Union, 1919 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
    - UBCJ, 1924, 1955, 1967, 1971; 1955; 1967; 1971 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - Carpenters District, Council of Bridgeport, 1950 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Subseries C: By-Laws, undated, 1908-1971
    - Local 43, Hartford, 1951 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
    - Local 97, Middletown, 1971 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
    - Local 127, Stamford, 1963 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
    - Local 137, Danbury, 1905, undated
    - Local 196, Greenwich, 1915, 1950, 1962, 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
    - Local 210, Stamford, 1920, 1929, 1937 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
    - Local 216, Torrington, 1908 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
    - Local 409, New Canaan, 1929 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
    - Local 1512, Middletown, 1949 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - Subseries D: Agreements, undated, 1908-1981
    - Journeyman Barbers International, manual, 1935 (Box 1:, Folder 19a)
    - Local 409 and building contractors, undated (Box 1:, Folder 20)
    - UBCJ, Town of Norfolk, 1906 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
    - UBCJ, Jurisdictional claims, 1917 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
    - Bridgeport Carpenters and General Contractors Association of Bridgeport, 1959-1961 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
    - Local 210 and Association of General Contractors of Connecticut, Inc, 1973 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
    - Local 210 and Residential Contractors, 1973-1974 (Box 1:, Folder 27)
    - Local 210 and Hatel Bailey, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 28)
    - Connecticut State Council of Carpenters: Statewide Residential Agreement, 1975-1977 (Box 1:, Folder 29)
    - Local 964 and Rockland County Carpenters Association, Inc., 1977 (Box 1:, Folder 30)
    - Local 115, Sick leave benefits and by-laws, 1981 (Box 1:, Folder 31)
    - Local 964, Vacation fund, undated (Box 1:, Folder 32)
  - Subseries E: Anniversaries and Celebrations, 1969-1977
    - Stamford Labor Council "Labor Man of the Year", 1969, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 33)
    - Local 927, 68th Anniversary, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 34)
    - Local 115, 86th Anniversary, 1971 (Box 1:, Folder 35)
    - Local 210, 75th Anniversary, Stamford, 1972 (Box 1:, Folder 36)
    - Local 210, UBCJ 100th Anniversary, Norwalk, Western Connecticut, 1981 (Box 1:, Folder 38)
  - Subseries F: Finance, 1922-1976
    - Local 210, Ten-year five percent bond, 1922 (Box 1:, Folder 39)
    - Local 210, Resignation of Financial Secretary Frank Benny, 1954 (Box 1:, Folder 40)
    - Connecticut State Council of Carpenters: Pension Fund, 1928-1975 (Box 1:, Folder 41)
    - Local 210 Cash Balance in Checking Account Reports, 1972-1974 (Box 1:, Folder 42)
    - CHOP Committee, Stamford, 1973 (Box 1:, Folder 43)
    - Local 210, Welfare Fund Annual Report, 1973-1974 (Box 1:, Folder 44)
    - Carpenter's General Fund and Analysis, 1974-1975 (Box 1:, Folder 45)
    - Carpenters Health Fund, 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 46)
    - Local 210, financial statements, 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 47)
    - Local 210, Bond reports, 1975-1976 (Box 1:, Folder 48)
  - Subseries G: Publications, undated, 1920-1982
    - News clippings, 1970-1974 (Box 1:, Folder 49)
    - Home and building products advertisements, undated [ca. 1920-1950] (Box 1:, Folder 50)
  - Subseries H: Photographs, undated, 1950-1970
    - UBCJ Executive Headquarters, Stamford, CT (photos and blueprints), 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 51)
    - Unidentified photos, undated (Box 1:, Folder 52)
    - National Home of UBCJ (Lakewood, Florida), Post cards, undated (Box 1:, Folder 53)
    - Local 210, unidentified photos, 1950 (Box 1:, Folder 54)
- Series II: Minute books, undated, 1901-1977